2018年2月6日
A few days ago on the 6th of February 2018
这个YouTuber把重型猎鹰Falcon Heavy说成Falcon 9 Heavy 你们知道是啥就行
SpaceX的重型猎鹰火箭首飞
SpaceX's first test launch of the Falcon 9 heavy the most powerful rocket since
成为土星五号、能源号以来成功发射的推力最大的火箭，载荷是马一龙的红色
the Saturn 5 successfully launched a payload of Elon Musk's own cherry red
特斯拉跑车，上面有个叫Starman的小人
Tesla roadster complete with a Starman mannequin first into orbit and then on
原定去火星，实际是进入了绕日椭圆轨道
what was meant to be a journey to Mars but now looks more like an elliptical
远日点达到了火星木星之间的小行星带
orbit extending out to the asteroid belt between Mars and Jupiter.
当重型猎鹰成功把载荷送进深空的时候
Whilst the Falcon 9 heavy proved that it could launch a payload into deep space
Starman和跑车的应该会很悠闲
Starman and the Roasters journey itself is going to be a pretty leisurely one just
就像我们发射进深空的所有其他东西一样，不管是假人、跑车还是
like everything else we've launched into deep space fine for mannequins, cars and
真正的探测器，但对人来说就不这样了。去火星平均要花九个月
robotic probes but not so good for humans. With an average time of nine
中间要面临辐射、失重
months to get to Mars the risk from radiation, weightlessness and
心理、精神上的问题，更不用说他们还要携带大量物资
psychological issues is high, not to mention with supplies they need to carry
就算他们能在飞船上种菜、循环用水，要带的东西也不少
even if they're going to grow their own food and recycle their own water.
但如果你能缩短旅途时间，之前提到的所有风险
But if you can reduce the time it takes to get there all these things become much more
都会变得轻松，然而人类曾经研究过二十来年的核动力火箭
manageable, however there is a technology using nuclear power that was developed
美国在上世纪五十年代到七十年代最开始搞
for about 20 years from the 50s to the 1970s originally by the US and the
后来苏联为了火星任务也在七八十年代开始研究，但后来随着
Soviets for Mars missions proposed in the 1970s and 80s but was shelved after
任务取消也跟着搁置。但现在人类又对火星感兴趣了
the demise of the missions themselves. Now with our revived interest in Mars
所以用于深空探测的核动力火箭也再次写入日程
missions and trips to deep space nuclear-powered rockets are back on the
从而减少太空旅行时间、增加运力
agenda as a way to cut transit time and carry greater payloads.
但我们得先说明，核动力火箭是只用在太空内的
But we have to make a distinction here the nuclear rocket engines are only for use in space
因为这类火箭相比于传统化学火箭推力非常小
because they have a much lower thrust to weight ratio compared to chemical
所以将仍然使用化学火箭将载荷送进地球轨道
rockets and so chemical ones will still be doing the heavy lifting from Earth
当到了太空，不需要克服地球重力了，核动力火箭
into orbit but once they're an away from a gravity of Earth nuclear engines can
就会高效得多。如今的化学火箭虽然推力大
be much more efficient. Now as powerful as chemical rockets are
但它们有个问题是除了燃料还得携带氧化剂
they have a problem they need to carry not only the fuel but also the oxygen
才能燃烧，这使得火箭多了很多重量，也减少了能带的载荷量
allow it to burn which makes the Rockets much heavier and also reduces the payload available.
第一种核动力火箭，热核火箭
The first type of nuclear rocket, the nuclear thermal one
不需要液氧就能工作
does away with the liquid oxygen altogether and instead passes liquid
它内部液氢流过核反应堆后被加热
hydrogen fuel through a nuclear reactor to heat it up to a superheated gas, this
然后这股热气从尾喷口喷出，这步和化学火箭一样
hot gas has been ejected from the engine in the same way as a chemical rocket and
于是就产生了推力。两者区别在于，化学火箭
that's where it creates its thrust. The difference is that when a chemical
发动机燃烧氢氧生成水，水很重
rocket engine burns hydrogen & oxygen the byproduct which is water vapour is heavy
在相同温度下速度就慢
and therefore as a given temperature its velocity is lower and therefore the
产生的推力就小。而核火箭不燃烧氢
thrust created is less. Because a nuclear thermal engine doesn't burn the hydrogen
它只是把氢加热，当热的氢气被排出时
it just heats it up it's still pure hydrogen when it leaves the rocket
由于氢是最轻的元素，温度相同时它排出的速度也是最快的
engine and as hydrogen is the lightest element its exit velocity is the highest
于是产生的推力也更大
for a given temperature and therefore the thrust is considerably more
火箭的燃烧效率单位是秒
A rockets efficiency or how well it makes use of its fuel is measured in seconds
物理名称叫“比冲”，意义是
of specific impulse sounds complicated but put simply it means how long in
单位质量燃料可以单位推力推动几秒
seconds one pound of propellant can deliver one pound of thrust
坠吼的化学火箭比冲可以达到450秒，而早期的
the best chemical rockets have a specific impulse around 450 seconds whereas the early
测试核火箭就拥有高达900的比冲，几乎是最强化学火箭的两倍
test nuclear Rockets had a specific impulse of around 900 seconds twice as efficient.
另外由于你不用带大量的
Now couple that to a fact when you don't now need to carry a lot of
液氧，使得你要么可以飞得更快
heavy liquid oxygen around with you and this means you can either go faster or
要么可以带更重的载荷。从五十年代中期开始就已经有这方面的理论研究
carry greater payloads. From the mid-1950s this principle was studied
新墨西哥州的洛斯阿拉莫斯原子能实验室当年就做了广泛的研究
extensively at the Atomic Energy Commission laboratory at Los Alamos in
当时的项目名称叫Rover
New Mexico through a program called Project Rover.
1959年，一个叫Kiwi的实验反应堆在内华达州的Jackass Flasts试验场准备测试
By 1959 an experimental reactor called Kiwi who was ready for testing in Jackass Flats in Nevada
最后成功达到了100兆瓦，最后在
and successfully ran at a power of a 100 megawatts and then up to a full
1962年达到了1000兆瓦的功率。后来，把Kiwi改成
power rating of 1000 megawatts in 1962. The program to turn Kiwi into a working
能用的发动机的工程全程叫“核动力发动机火箭载具应用”，缩写是NERVA
engine was called nuclear engines rocket vehicle applications or NERVA
1967年测试再次成功，NRX-A6发动机
again the tests were successful and in 1967 the NRX-A6
成功点火一小时，而且如果不是测试场地氢气有限，还能工作更久
engine fired successfully for an hour as the tests continued the engine
runtime was only really limited by the supplies of liquid hydrogen at the test site.
虽然发动机测试结果说明这个概念OK，但其他方面还有问题
Whilst these test engines proved the concept there were still issues the
保护飞行乘组、飞控设备不受辐射的保护罩的重量太大
weight of the shielding to protect for crew and the control electronics from
使得引擎重量过大，还有个问题是
the radiation made the engines very heavy, there was also the problem of what
如果核动力火箭在发射台上出问题
would happen if a nuclear engine rocket were to fail on a launch pad or were to
或者从轨道失控再入的时候，放射性物质一旦落到
fall back to earth from orbit and spread highly radioactive material over
有人的地方后果很严重。同时它还有过热的问题
potentially highly populated areas. And there was also issues with overheating
燃料本来可以作为冷却剂的，但如果燃料用完后发动机没关好怎么办
if the fuel which acted as a coolant ran out before the engine was shut down properly.
但经过几年的测试，这些发动机都已经准备好进太空
But after years of testing they were deemed ready for use in space and
NRX发动机都打算在70年代上太空了
NRX seemed to be on track to make it there by the late 1970s.
在铁幕另一边，苏联首席火箭工程师科罗廖夫
On the other side of the Iron Curtain the Soviet chief rocket designer Sergey Korolyov
也打算让他的N1超级烟花带着核动力上面级
expected his N1 super heavy lift rocket to carry a nuclear upper stage,
从而让他的火箭拥有星际航行能力。他的团队考虑了几种方案
giving the vehicle a formidable interplanetary capability. His team considered several options
要么在三级火箭上放两个核动力级
either two nuclear other stages on a three-stage rocket
或者在二级或者三级火箭上放一个核动力级，无论哪种构型
or a single nuclear stage on a two or three stage rocket. With any of these options the N1
N1火箭的上面级都要捆一堆核动力火箭
upper stages would have had to cluster large numbers of nuclear engines
比美国的设计方案多多了。但热核火箭上面级
together many more than on the American designs. But a nuclear thermal upper
去火星的载荷量的计算理论值仍然比传统化学火箭多50%
stage was calculated to be able to deliver up to 50% more payload to Mars than a chemical one.
同时，热核火箭也并不是唯一的选择
However the nuclear thermal engines weren't the only options available on the table.
科罗廖夫其实青睐于另一种核能方式
Korolev favored another way of harnessing atomic power,
把核反应堆与电推引擎结合在一起，推力更小
pairing a nuclear reactor with an electric ion engine although the system provided much less thrust.
但相比于热核火箭，这种方法长时间提供小推力更有效率
It was even more efficient and would provide a low
thrust for a very long period of time compared to the quick bursts like the nuclear thermal ones.
最近几年由于太阳帆板技术的进步
In recent times advances in solar panel
这类核反应堆+电推的设计就略显多余了
design has made nuclear reactor powered iron engines much less likely but for
但对于土星以外的深空任务，没有足够的太阳辐射
deep space missions beyond Saturn where there is not enough sunlight to operate
核动力火箭则又变成唯一的选择
solar panels successfully nuclear power becomes pretty much the only option.
计算显示相比传统化学火箭，电推能提升70%的运力
Calculations showed that ion drives will be able to transport 70% more payload
than chemical engines on a mission to Mars.
N1项目差不多嗝屁了以后
After the N1 rocket quite literally fell by the wayside
苏联火星任务的大旗就交到了切洛梅手里
the chief designer Vladimir Chelomei was in pole position
to design a rocket for the Soviet manned Mars mission.
MK700上面级将用UR700火箭多次发射，然后在轨组装
The enormous MK 700 was to be assembled in orbit with multiple launches for the modular UR700 rocket.
MK700上面级将靠其VG设计局的RD-0410热核火箭发动机实现星际航行
The MK 700 would make its interplanetary burn with a
nuclear thermal engine built by Valentin Glushko's design bureau and called the RD-0410.
发动机在哈萨克斯坦东部进行了测试，达到了910秒的比冲
The engine made it as far as testing at the test site in north
east kazakhstan demonstrating yet again Glushko's mastery of rocket engine
发动机在哈萨克斯坦东部进行了测试，达到了910秒的比冲
efficiency the RD-0410 showed a capability of 910 seconds of specific impulse.
然而到了1972年，公众与政府
However by 1972 and due to the loss of
逐渐对太空失去兴趣，NASA研发
interest in space by the public and the government in the US funding for
火星任务与NERVA引擎的资金也被国会撤回
NASA's mars mission and NERVA was cancelled by congress.
后来航天飞机把目标聚焦在近地空间，核动力火箭更是没有了用武之地
As the space shuttle returned to focus to low-earth orbit where nuclear engines weren't required
苏联那边也转而研发暴风雪号来与美国抗衡
and the soviet priority was to match this capability,
使得他们研发核动力飞船的计划也取消了
their research into nuclear-powered spacecraft also stalled.
然而这些事在里根总统80年代末提出星球大战计划的时候又被翻出来了
However things picked up again with President Ronald Reagan's Star Wars initiative in the late 1980s project
利用球床反应堆设计的Timberwind发动机
Timberwind advanced the engines using a pebble bed reactor design and increased
达到了接近1000秒的比冲，而这个项目也直接引领了
the specific impulse to nearly 1,000 seconds it also led to the development
后来现代的碳基复合材料的研发，但它仍然遇到了一些技术问题
of modern carbon composite materials but it also faced technical issues which
使它很难用于太空，最终也惨遭撤资
would have made it very difficult to use as a space based engine system and funding was eventually dropped.
最近，毛子国家原子能中心的工程师正在研发
More recently Russian engineers at the State Energy Corporation ROSATOM are working on a
一种新的核电推进系统“TEM”
form of nuclear electric propulsion called 'TEM'.
缩写全称是"运输能量模块"，反应堆是双模式工作的
The acronym translates to transport an energy unit the name indicates a nuclear reactor capable of
当发动机不工作时，它能切换为
bimodal operation that is when it's not powering engines it can be switched to a
低功率模式，为飞船居住舱等其他系统供电
low power mode to power the living quarters and other onboard systems.
根据TEM的设计者说，TEM打算今年进行一次地面测试
According to the designers TEM has a goal of testing a ground-based engine
并于2025年发射一个发动机原型，如果不被撤资的话
this year and launching a prototype by 2025 if funding can be secured.
这项技术理论上能让地火旅行时间缩短到45天
The technology could in theory enable a journey from Earth to Mars in just 45 days.
NASA也在进行新的研究
NASA is also conducting new research into rapid transit technologies
来缓解人类长期在星际环境下受到的影响
to mitigate the long-term effects of interplanetary space on the human body
与毛子一样，NASA也把热核火箭作为一种解决方案
Like Russia, NASA sees nuclear thermal propulsion as a solution here the goal
当前研究的目标是降低成本，同时降低核燃料的风险
of the current research is to reduce for cost and risk of the nuclear fuel by
方法是研发一种低浓铀燃料
developing a suitable form of low enriched uranium with a concentration of
铀-235含量只有3-4%，相比于早期版本使用的武器级的90%
3-4% uranium-235 compared to a 90% concentration
of weapons-grade fuel in the earlier designs.
这段视频见av722359的2P(1P也超级牛逼)
NASA的研究应该会首次应用到类似“哥白尼号”这样的地火转移飞船上
NASA's research may well find its first use in a spacecraft like this the Copernicus mass transfer vehicle
作为已经被取消的星座计划里的一部分
conceived as part of the now cancelled constellation program,
“哥白尼号”B型当年设想是用NASA的SLS Block2构型在轨组装
Copernicus B is being considered for an in orbit assembly using NASA's upcoming SLS block 2 launch system.
飞船一头的居住舱可以对接猎户座飞船
At one end of Copernicus the Orion spacecraft would
dock with a manned payload living space.
尾部由三台热核火箭发动机驱动来实现星际旅行
Copernicus would then make its interplanetary journey using three nuclear thermal engines each capable of
单台推力11.3吨
producing 25,000 pounds of thrust.
核动力引擎的效率能
The efficiency of the nuclear engines would
让飞船在一百天内到达火星，虽然没有之前说的
enable a trip to Mars in a hundred days not quite as quickly as were proposed
毛子的发动机快，但相比传统化学火箭已经是很大的进步了
Russian mission but still a significant improvement over traditional chemical
同时“哥白尼”号的反应堆也是支持双模式的
engines and also Copernicus would be capable of bimodal reactor operation.
所以对于未来的载人任务使用核动力火箭你是怎么想的呢？
So what do you think of using nuclear Rockets for future manned missions?
欢迎在评论区留下你的看法
Let me know in the comments below.
别忘了这个YouTuber还有个非死不可页面
Now don't forget we also have the curious droid Facebook page if you have
有建议可以去那提，还有个Patreon页面，可以资助这位YouTuber
any suggestions for future videos and a patreon page if you're interested in
所以感谢大家的观看，记得投币点赞收藏分享关注哦！
becoming a patron or if you already are one. So it just remains for me to say
字幕翻译给虫
thanks for watching and please subscribe, thumbs up and share